A Finding Aid to the Alice Neel Papers, 1933-1983, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Alice Neel papers
1933-1983
Archives of American Art
Neel, Alice, 1900-1984
AAA.neelalic
Archival Resource Key
1 Linear foot
The papers of New York painter Alice Neel measure 1.0 linear foot and date from 1933 to 1983. The bulk of the collection documents the last fifteen years of Neel's career as an artist. Found within the papers are letters from galleries, museums, and art organizations; writings and notes by Neel; exhibition catalogs, clippings, and other printed material; and photographs depicting Neel, exhibitions, and her artwork.
Provenance
The collection was donated from 1974 to 1983 by Alice Neel.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art are printed material on Romare Bearden, Alice Neel, and Howard Newman, 1975-1990, compiled by Dennis Florio, and a videorecording of "Art and Alice Neel," 1975, recorded as part of University of Georgia Television station WGTV's "Forum" program.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reel 4964 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Alice Neel (1900-1984) was a painter in New York, NY. She was known for her portraits of New York artists and intellectuals. Neel studied painting at the Philadelphia School of Design for Women (now the Moore College of Art and Design) from 1921-1925. She married Cuban artist Carlos Enríquez, and they briefly lived in Havana, Cuba. After the break-up of their marriage, she settled in New York City. During the 1930s she worked for the Public Works of Art Project and the Works Progress Administration, painting scenes of urban poverty and developing her distinctive portrait style. She pursued a career as a figurative painter during a period when abstraction was favored, and she did not begin to gain critical praise for her work until the 1960s. Neel received an honorary doctorate from the Moore College of Art and Design in 1971 and a retrospective of her work was held at the Whitney Museum in 1974. During the last decade of her life she finally received extensive national recoginition for her paintings. Neel was also a notable public speaker and often spoke on the topic of women artists.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of New York painter Alice Neel measure 1.0 linear foot and date from 1933 to 1983. The bulk of the collection documents the last fifteen years of Neel's career as an artist. Found within the papers are letters from galleries, museums, and art organizations; writings and notes by Neel; exhibition catalogs, clippings, and other printed material; and photographs depicting Neel, exhibitions, and her artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as # series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Letters, circa 1968-1983 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 2: Writings and Notes, circa 1960-1979 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1933-1983 (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 4: Photographs, 1940-1983 (Box 1; 6 folders)
Portrait painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs; Notes; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Portrait painting -- 20th century -- United States; Women artists; Women painters
- Letters, circa 1968-1983; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  Letters are from galleries, museums, and art organizations and primarily concern Neel's work and art related activities. Also found are holiday and birthday cards from friends as well as fan mail. Included among the letters from 1977 are two color snapshots of Neel.
  Arrangement note
  Letters are arranged chronologically.
  - Letters, 1968-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1977; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
  - Letters, 1978; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - Letters, 1979; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
  - Letters, 1980; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
  - Letters, 1981-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letters, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1960-1979; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  This series includes artists' statements, Neel's acceptance speech for her degree, her Bloomsburg State College lecture, a one page reminiscence on Anton Refregier, and miscellaneous notes.
  - Writings, 1960-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Notes, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Printed Material, 1933-1983; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
  Printed material primarily document's Neels late career from 1970 to 1983. Included are announcements and exhibiton catalogs for solo and group shows, newspaper and magazine articles about Neel, and scattered press releases, flyers, and event brochures. Also found is a journal, Mother Number Six, which includes reproductions of Neel's portraits of Joe Gould.
  - Press Releases, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Exibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1933-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Exibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1970-1983; Archival Resource Key; (10 folders) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Exibition Announcements and Catalogs, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Programs, 1971-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Advertisements Brochures, 1978-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Clippings, undated, 1968-1983; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Journal, Mother Number Six, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1973, 1977-1981, Undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Photographs, 1940-1983; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1; 6 folders)
  Found in this series are eight photograph portraits of Alice Neel, including one of her in her studio in 1983, and photographs of exhibition openings at the Maxwell Gallery and the Graham Gallery. Photographs of these openings include her colleagues John Koch and Raphael Soyer. Photograph stills for the movie "Pull My Daisy" depict Neel and others. Also found are photographs of Neel's artwork and slides of an exhibtion installation at Akron Art Institute.
  - Photographs of Neel, 1940-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Photographs of Studio and Gallery Openings, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Stills from Motion Picture Film with Neel, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, circa 1981; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Slides of Installation at Akron Art Institute, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)